Guide to the S. Spafford Ackerly papers 2013.010
Brooklyn Historical Society
S. Spafford Ackerly papers
circa 1890 to 2013
Brooklyn Historical Society
Wurtman, Elizabeth A.
Ehrlich, Nancy S.
Warner, Carita A.
Ackerly, William C.
Ackerly, S. Spafford
2013.010
1.7 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 flat box
38.7 Megabytes in 16 digital files.
The papers document the life of psychiatrist Dr. S. Spafford Ackerly. The papers primarily consist of typescripts, photographs, publications, clippings, correspondence, transcripts, awards, and digital images, dating from circa 1890 to 2013, which were collected and assembled by his children. It also includes memorabilia owned by Dr. Ackerly, a scrapbook documenting his time at the Manual Training High School (Brooklyn, NY), and an audio cassette containing recordings of his memoirs.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life of psychiatrist Dr. S. Spafford Ackerly. The papers primarily consist of typescripts, photographs, publications, clippings, correspondence, transcripts, awards, and digital images, dating from circa 1890 to 2013, which were collected and assembled by his children. It also includes memorabilia owned by Dr. Ackerly, a scrapbook documenting his time at the Manual Training High School (Brooklyn, NY), and an audio cassette containing recordings of his memoirs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William C. Ackerly, Nancy S. Ehrlich, Carita A. Warner, and Elizabeth A. Wurtman (children of S. Spafford Ackerly), 2013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Biographical note
Dr. Samuel Spafford Ackerly (1895-1947), was a pioneering psychiatrist who specialized in the treatment of mental illness. He was born in Brooklyn, NY, on May 20, 1895, to George Briggs and Nancy Spafford (Brown) Ackerly, and resided at 647 Monroe Street. He attended the Manual Training High School in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn, graduating with honors in 1914. He then attended Wesleyan University, before joining the Armed Forces and serving in World War I, where he was wounded in 1918.
After recovering from his injuries, he attended Yale University Medical School, studying under Alfred Adler and graduating in 1925. He began his formal psychiatric training at the Westchester Division of the New York Hospital, then continued his studies in Massachusetts, London, and Vienna, before joining the University of Louisville faculty in 1932. He would remain at Louisville for the rest of his career.
The "Memorial to S. Spafford Ackerly, M.D." by Harry H. Moorehead and Frank J. Curran (1981) summarizes his career as follows:
"He had the first Commonwealth Fund Grant in Kentucky and was awarded one of the first teaching grants from N.I.M.H. He was awarded a Guggenheim fellowship. He was chairman of the Department of Psychiatry at the University of Louisville and the director of the Louisville Child Guidance Clinic. He founded the Kentucky Psychiatric Society, of which he served as president. He also served as vice-president of the American Psychiatric Association, and president of the American Orthopsychiatric Society. He was a charter fellow of the American College of Psychiatrists, a life fellow of the American College of Physicians, a founding member of the American Academy of Child Psychiatry, and a member if its council. He worked constantly with civic groups and with mayors, governors, and legislators during the years."
He married Carita Louise Clark on October 17, 1925, and had four children, Dr. William Clark Ackerly, Nancy (Steinson) Ehrlich, Elizabeth Wurtmann, and Carita A. Warner. He died on September 24, 1981, in Louisville, KY.
(The above is based on Ackerly's eulogies and curriculum vitae, which are found in the collection.)
Related Materials
The University of Louisville Kornhauser Health Sciences Library houses the Ackerly (S. Spafford), M.D. (1895-1981) papers, 1910s-1981, which consists of 10 linear feet of papers and oral histories conducted by Dr. Ackerly.
The Kornhauser Health Sciences Library also holds the Ackerly Oral History Project: Child Guidance Movement Pioneers collection.
According the correspondence found within the S. Spafford Ackerly collection, additional material may have been donated to Wesleyan University, Smith College, and the Boston Psychoanalytic Society and Institute Archives.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series 1: S. Spafford Ackerly binder, circa 1890-2013
Series 2: Manual Training High School scrapbook, 1914
Series 3: Memorabilia, 1943-1955
Series 4: S. Spafford Ackerly memoirs on audio cassette, 1971
Psychiatrists; Artifacts (object genre); Memorabilia; Scrapbooks; Publications; Typescripts; Medical sciences; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Kentucky; Genealogy; Photographs; Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Psychiatry; Mental health; World War, 1914-1918; Ackerly, S. Spafford; Wurtman, Elizabeth A.; Ehrlich, Nancy S.; Warner, Carita A.; Janes Methodist Episcopal Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Ackerly, William C.; Manual Training High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); University of Louisville; Adler, Alfred; Ackerly family
- Series 1: S. Spafford Ackerly binder, circa 1890 to 2013; 14545; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
  Arrangement
  The series was originally housed in a three-ring binder. The original order of the files has been maintained. Titles are derived from original labels found in the binder, and dates are derived from the content of the files.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of material which was collected by S. Spafford Ackerly and other members of the Ackerly family. The material was later organized by his children. The series primarily documents the life of S. Spafford Ackerly, but also includes information on his ancestors, as well as his wife, Carita C. Ackerly. Included in the series are documentation of Ackerly's youth in Brooklyn, his experiences as a soldier in World War I, and his professional career as a psychiatrist and administrator at the University of Louisville. The series consists of typescripts, photographs, publications, clippings, correspondence, transcripts, awards, and two digital images, dating from circa 1890 to 2013. Of note are two photographs of 647 Monroe St. in Brooklyn.
  - Ackerly and Brown families, undated; 14546 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Long Island history, 1903; 14547 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rev. Joshua Hartt, 1928; 14548 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family Reunion, 1991; 14549 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - S. Ackerly and brothers, circa 1917-1972; 14550 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General
    Includes photographs
  - Lavinia Ackerly, circa 1905-1919; 14551 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Early life / Brooklyn, circa 1970s; 14552 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manual Training High School of Brooklyn - Award of Honor, 1914; 14553 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Janes Church talk, circa 1920; 14554 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - George B. Ackerly, 1918-1936; 14555 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes 2 photographs of 647 Monroe St., Brooklyn
  - "Grace Under Pressure: In the Trenches and Beyond - A Story of Miracles OR An Historical Perspective on a Personal Journey" by Carita Ackerly Warner, 2005; 14556 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - S. Spafford Ackerly World War I portrait, circa 1918; 14557 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - World War I German propaganda leaflet, circa 1918; 14558 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Spafford Ackerly's War Memories (audio transcript), 1971; 14559 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "World War I Reminiscences" by S. Spafford Ackerly, circa 1970s; 14560 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Olympic Games - 1920 (audio transcript), 1920, 1971; 14561 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes photograph of Ackerly at Staten Island Army Hospital and clipping
  - Honorable Discharge, 1920; 14562 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - World War I letter and clippings, 1918; 14563 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ackerly's war buddy - Jack Carey, 1918-1920, 2005-2006; 14564 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes photograph of Ackerly at Carey's grave in Bony Cemetery, France
  - Carita C. Ackerly, circa 1911-1969; 14565 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Red Cross Hospital letter, 1919; 14566 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nannie B. Ackerly, circa 1890-1991; 14567 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1960s, 2012; 14568 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Connecticut Department of Health certificate, 1930; 14569 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Letter to the Children" by S. Spafford Ackerly and William C. Ackerly letter, 1979, 2012; 14570 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dr. Alfred Adler portrait, 1927; 14571 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Articles and papers by S. Spafford Ackerly, 1927-1966; 14572 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Veterans Administration correspondence, 1934; 14573 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Legislative proposals, 1926-1948; 14574 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Proposed School Mental Health Program, 1958; 14575 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Professional Work, 1940-1989; 14576 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Eulogies, 1981-1982; 14577 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence regarding collection donations, 2000-2007; 14578 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Reflections in Old Age" by S. Spafford Ackerly, circa 1981; 14579 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Portraits of family members (digital images), circa 19th century, 2013; 14580 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series 2: Manual Training High School scrapbook, 1914; 14581; 1.2 Linear Feet in 1 flat box (Box 2, Folder -)
  The series consists of a scrapbook containing clippings related to the Manual Training High School of Brooklyn, dating from 1914. The scrapbook was assembled by S. Spafford Ackerly, who was a student at the time. In addition to the clippings, the scrapbook includes a senior prom booklet, and two copies of a senior class performance program.
- Series 3: Memorabilia, 1911 to 1955; 14582; 4 items (Box 2, Folder -)
  The Memorabilia series consists of 3 medals attached to an inscribed pen knife on a chain (dating from 1943, 1946, and 1955), and one medal which Ackerly obtained while competing for the Janes Methodist Episcopal Church in 1911. The series includes handwritten identifications of the objects by his daughter, Nancy S. Ehrlich. This series also includes digital photographs of memorbilia, including a certificate from the State of Connecticut Department of Health, a certificate from the General Organization of the Manual Training High School of Brooklyn (Award of Honor), newspaper clippings, testimonial dinner at the Pendennis Club in 1957, book cover of Fifty Years of Psychiatry in Louisville.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
- Series 4: S. Spafford Ackerly memoirs on audio cassette, 1971; 14584; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Series contains one audio cassette containing recordings of S. Spafford Ackerly. Side A is labeled "War Experiences - Spafford Ackerly - Lyme, NH - 8-23-71" and Side B is labeled "Spafford Ackerly with grandchildren - Fawcett Kids - 12". The audio cassette's case is labeled "For Roger Fawcett - S. Spafford Ackerly Tapes". A transcript of Side A is available in Series 1 (Box 1 - Folder 14).